[Music]
Stanford University all right we've
really studied two different theories a
little bit quantum electrodynamics and
quantum chromodynamics both of them are
gauge theories in fact just about all of
nature as we know it in one way or
another is controlled by gauge theories
of different kinds and so I ought to
tell you what a gauge theory is now I'm
not going to get into any depth what
gauge symmetry is I'm going to tell you
what gauge what a gauge Theory is in
more or less the minimal mathematical
way first and simplest gauge theory is
Maxwell's theory Maxwell's theory of
light or Maxwell's theory of
electromagnetism let's not worry about
what the word gauge means when we may go
through it later but not now
but what it is is a theory of fields
which have all of the properties of the
electromagnetic field the
electromagnetic field has six components
three components of electric field three
components of magnetic field you can
represent those six components in terms
of a four vector called the vector
potential I'll just write it down for
you where it's not going to play any big
role today anyway
but just to tell you there's a four
vector that's generally called a and it
has an index mu it has four components a
zero that's the time component of it and
the three space components a one two and
three or a x y&z let's not write them
out in detail so it contains a three
vector and a fourth component a not the
significance of a nought is that it's
the electrostatic potential it's the
thing whose gradient is the
check force okay so for example the
electric force on a charged particle
it's just gotten by multiplying the
electric charge by the gradient or the
derivative F X derivative of a not with
respect to X so it's just the
electrostatic potential it's measured in
volts or in particle physics of course
it's not measured in volts volts per
unit charge excuse me
both yeah measured in in whatever way
you measure electrostatic potential
that's the meaning of a nought I notice
first of all oh and of course this is
the electric field this is the electric
field it has three components derivative
with respect to X Y or Z so it's the
gradient the gradient of a right and the
gradient of a is just called the
electric field so the electric field is
determined by the gradient of a knot and
the magnetic field is determined by also
derivatives also derivatives of the
vector potential and in fact the
magnetic field is the curl of the vector
potential so one of two ways you can
study electrodynamics either in terms of
the electric and magnetic fields of
which there are six or in terms of the
vector potential of which there are four
but they're equivalent descriptions of
electrodynamics and we won't we won't go
into Maxwell's equations but let me just
remind you that Maxwell's equations give
rise to electromagnetic waves an
electromagnetic wave is a wave of
electric and magnetic field and a
typical electric magnetic wave has a
direction in space that it moves let's
just represent it by an arrow and it has
a polarization to understand what the
polarization means you have to think
about the electric and magnetic fields
and the electron-electron
here's the electric field for example
the whole thing moves with the speed of
light but at any given instant the
electric field might look like that and
the magnetic field is always
perpendicular to the electric field try
to draw see if I can give a drawing it's
a imagine in the electric field is in
the horizontal plane and it's always
perpendicular to thee let's see is this
going to it's always perpendicular like
so in appropriate units the electric and
magnetic field are equal to each other
and perpendicular this would be a plane
polarized electromagnetic wave and the
plane polarized electromagnetic wave the
direction of polarization which of
course is always perpendicular to the
direction of motion the direction of
polarization is determined by the
electric field so the electric field
determines the direction of polarization
and that's electromagnetism and a lots
electromagnetic waves in a nutshell the
other thing of course about
electromagnetic waves is that there are
sources the sources are charges and
currents but let's particularly focus on
the sources of the electric field the
sources of the electric field are
electric charge and to just draw a
picture to put it at the level of
pictures every electric charge creates
an electric field the electric field
lines never end
except on other charges a positive
convention the convention is a positive
electric charge puts out a electric
field which is radially outward falls
off as one over R squared you can
imagine that the number of electric
field lines coming out of a charge is
fixed proportional to the charge and the
for the number of electric field lines
passing through any sphere is the same
no matter how far the sphere is to say
that mathematically the integral of the
electric field over the sphere is the
same wherever you go however far out you
go that's Gauss's law but Scouse is law
and that Gauss's law has a very strong
consequence if you don't have any other
charges in the system let's say just a
plus charge then you can't get and the
rule is electric lines only end on
charges then there's no way to get rid
of a charge no way to get it rid of a
charge if you try to get rid of the
charge either the electric field has to
suddenly disappear Everywhere's that
would violate the rules of the speed of
light that you can't send a signal
faster than the speed of light so
instead if you said that a wave moved
outward of missing electric field that
also wouldn't make sense not unless
there were charges at the endpoints of
the electric field so all this would
really be is this would not be the
elimination of the charge it would just
be taking the charge and sending it out
as a shell would be a shell of charge
going out the charge would not have
disappeared so it's a consequence of
deep consequence of the structure the
mathematical structure Gauss's law and
other laws that electric charge is
conserved that is the arm essence of a
gauge Theory essence of a gauge theory
maxwell like fields i'll use the word
maxwell like because they're not all
truly Maxwell's electromagnetic
filled maxwell like fields consisting of
electric like and magnetic like fields
if the a life the gauge field is weakly
coupled and i will tell you what that
means later but it basically means that
if the interactions between the parts of
the electromagnetic field are weak
enough that they don't interact with
each other seriously then the motion of
a gauge field is exactly the same as a
light wave that will have a polarization
it will move down the axis with the
speed of light unless something else
unless it's something in the dynamics
that changes that are naively at least
it's in every way similar to the
electromagnetic field the only
difference is it also has sources every
gauge field has sources analogous to the
electric charge but it may not be the
electric charge it might be something
else let me give you an example which is
an unphysical example unphysical not
because it's inconsistent but because it
just happens not to be true as far as we
know there is another quantity in nature
called the baryon number it's simply the
number of quarks
juster but it's a conserved quantity and
you could imagine that baryon number is
the source of our Burien number is not
electric charge why not well because
protons and neutrons have it so it is
not electric charge but it could be the
source of its own gauge field if it were
that would mean that there would be
forces between protons neutrons protons
protons neutrons neutrons that would be
analogous to the Coulomb forces between
charges except they would have nothing
to do with electric charge they would
have only to do with baryon number so
for example two
Jex with the same baryon number would
repel each other a proton and a neutron
would repel each other because they have
the same baryon number a proton and a
proton would repel on the other hand
proton and antiproton having opposite
baryon number would attract now the only
rub in this ointment is that there is no
such gauge field coupled to the baryon
number baryon number does not come with
a field like this that surrounds it and
no long-range force associated with it
so Berrien number is not an example
color is an example and the color forces
of quantum chromodynamics also or before
i do that one one or two other points
one or two other points the other point
of course is this is a completely
classical description of an
electromagnetic wave the corresponding
quantum mechanical description is in
terms of quanta but of course if we
think of quanta as particles at least
that's the about the only mental picture
that we have to describe these do these
discrete little objects the discreet
little objects which drawing them of
course is always misleading but let me
draw our photon is a photon a little
point that little photon has a position
moves of the speed of light but also it
has a little flag associated with it and
that little flag is this polarization I
won't try to draw a flag on it in other
words it has a pointer which either
points this way this way or somewhere is
in between that indicates the
polarization of the electromagnetic wave
of which it is a quantum that's a
complicated statement but you I think
you get it so photons come with
polarization and that polarization in
principle can be rotated you can rotate
it by sending it through a quarter wave
plate or in any number of ways rays
[Music]
and that's photons it's the photon
theory of electromagnetism and in the
quantum theory one can think of the
Coulomb field as roughly speaking a
field set up by the emission and
absorption of photons emission and
absorption of these photons okay so
that's that's electrodynamics and a
nutshell electrons are charged protons
are charged and so forth and the and
they interact in this way with the gauge
field another aspect of gauge fields
I've already mentioned it that there's
always conservation laws associated with
them namely conservation of the sources
but conservation laws in both quantum
mechanics and classical mechanics are
always associated with symmetries
symmetries of some sort or another are
always behind conservation laws the
conservation of electric charge we've
talked about that and I showed you how
if you study the quantum mechanics of
electrons in terms of charged particles
in general there's a wave field
describing those particles this could be
the electron and the symmetry associated
with the conservation of charge is just
the multiplication of the field by a
phase so that was the simplest example
of a gauge theory a gauge charge meaning
the electric charge and a symmetry that
goes along with the conservation of that
charge those things go together okay
well let me just very quickly remind you
how it worked in quantum chromodynamics
in quantum chromodynamics a more
complicated structure you do have
maxwell like fields let's label them
the Maxwell like fields are labeled
by indices so in quantum quote let's
continue to call them AE there is no
universal symbol for the gauge field of
quantum chromodynamics sometimes it's
called G sometimes it's called a
sometimes it's called B sometimes it's
called C I'm going to call it a but in
order to distinguish it from the
electromagnetic field we give it some
indices I and J it's a matrix now it's a
matrix and that matrix transforms under
a group the group was su 3 so let me
just remind you very very quickly that
we started thinking about su 3 not by
thinking about gluons this is of course
would be the gluon field but by thinking
about quarks so a quark was an object
which we called q q could stand for the
quantum field of the quark and it has an
index the index that's not the up-down
index it's not the charm strange index
will come to that sooner or later it is
the color index red green or blue I
takes on three values and the symmetry
operation is not multiplying by e to the
I theta but multiplying by a unitary
special unitary matrix u IJ gives us Q
prime I that was the symmetry operation
which is a kind of rotation in a in a in
a kind of three-dimensional complex
space don't confuse it with ordinary
three-dimensional space
this was the symmetry operation and one
would say that the Q's think of them as
particles if you like the Q's form a
representation of su 3 which is called
the mental representation it's called
the fundamental representation it has
three entries red green and blue
sometimes it's called the defining
representation it's the smallest
non-trivial representation and it just
has just can be thought of as a three
component vector one two three and the
unitary matrices can be thought of as
matrices 3x3 matrices ok we've gone
through that the other thing that I told
you is that anti quarks or anti
particles in general are represented by
the complex conjugate fields field which
are simply the complex conjugates of the
original ones the relation the
mathematical relation between particle
and anti particle or the wave functions
of particles and antiparticles that
relationship is complex conjugation so
we could ask how do anti particles
transform well we simply realize that if
you want to transform the complex
conjugate field you should use the
complex conjugate matrix if you multiply
Q by you to get Q Prime then you must
multiply Q star by u star to get Q prime
star the set of matrices you are called
a representation of the group the set of
matrices u star are a distinct and
different representation in the group
and the language one would use is that
quarks and antiquarks are described by
the three-dimensional the
three-dimensional representation and we
could call a three star meaning complex
conjugate it's usually indicated by a
bar two different representations of SU
three
how many eight nine actually well sorry
you asked me how many matrices there are
the number of generators is eight yeah
because these matrices are assumed to be
special unitary matrices now you can ask
and it's interesting to ask what we're
kind of theory would you make if you
didn't insist that they be special and
I'll tell you another time maybe later
but they're but not now okay now what is
a IJ a IJ has two indices and the way to
think about it is that one of those it
is mathematically got the same group
theory structure the same symmetry
structure as having a quark J and an
antiquark
ie in other words this is an object
whose indices transform one index as the
three-dimensional representation and the
other index as the three-bar another way
to think about it is it has all of the
properties with respect to the symmetry
not with respect to all physical
properties but with respect to the way
it transforms it transforms as if it
were a quark and an antiquark sitting on
top of each other not at spin just its
color as if it were a quark and an
antiquark with one special rule namely
the trace of a IJ vanishes the singlet
singlet that you can make the piece
which has no transformation property
under the group at all that you can kill
and forget about that's why there are
eight AI J's instead of nine so a IJ is
like a thing with a quark and an
antiquark index but because it has a
quark and an antiquark index it also
transforms when you under the SU 3
transformation group in that sense it's
different than the
photon the photon is completely
electrically neutral it's filled the
photon field does not get a phase when
you rotate the electron wave function
electrons go to e to the I theta x
electrons positrons go to e to the minus
I theta x positrons photons do nothing
that's because they don't have electric
charge but the gluons they do have color
now what kind of color do they have they
have the color of a particle and an
antiparticle I say well particle and an
antiparticle shouldn't have any color
but they do because you could have a red
particle and a blue anti particle a red
that would make a thing which was not
really neutral which knew about color so
gluons do have color and they have color
in what is called the adjoint
representation which is the
representation of the eight generators
okay now what about what about the
interaction between quarks incidentally
are there are many other gauge theories
of interest they're all pretty similar
to each other the group might not be su3
it might be su - it might be su 4 it
might be su 10 it might be anything and
the objects of the group might not be
called quarks nevertheless or the
fundamental objects of the group the
analogs of quarks might be called
something else they might have a
different name R but they would be
objects which had a single index there
the anti objects would also have a
single index above the complex conjugate
kind and the analog of the gluons which
are called gauge bosons gauge bosons the
Maxwell like fields always have one
index of the
particle type and another index of the
anti particle type so that means let's
see if we call if we're talking about su
n that means how many generators
altogether well n times n is N squared
minus 1 for the trace so it's N squared
minus 1 distinct gluons now what is the
what is the connection between the
quarks or more generally or more
generally the particles which transform
like quarks perhaps in the more general
way what's the connection between them
and the gauge bosons and I've explained
that to you before but let me just
remind you again if you have a quark
labeled by I where I could be red green
or blue and another quark labeled by J
that the ithe quark can become the Jade
quark
if a gauge boson is emitted what kind of
gauge boson well as I showed you before
the way to think about it is just to
think about these lines running through
the diagram I runs right through so
that's I and J also runs right through
except when J is pointing downward it
should be thought of as the anti the
analog of an anti particle and so an I
would become a J by emitting a quanta a
quantum of the field a there's a ji or
IJ I think IJ
no ji doesn't matter very much by
emitting a gluon of the IJ type an eigth
article becomes a J particle and that is
one of the basic interactions of quantum
chromo of gauge theories in general of
gauge theories in general fundamental
objects analogous to quark
gauge bosons analogous to the gluons and
they rule about emission and absorption
that you have to follow the lines and
never lose and index but now that raises
something new if a gluon itself has the
properties of a quark and an antiquark
so let's say this is the I J DH kind of
glue on well the I J kind of glue on can
also emit a glue on how would it do it
the IJ glue on could become the i k f--
glue on i j let's say red green blue on
could become the red blue glow on as
long as the indices make sense and
they're followed anti k here alright so
this would be a interaction in which a
glue on of type IJ became a glue on of
type i k and a glue on they are glue on
of type K J glue one of type K J the
order of iron K matters or a KJ is not
the same as a JK but um are alright that
introduces something absolutely new
which is not in electrodynamics namely
that the gluons themselves are charged
particles and therefore exert forces on
each other they exert forces in a way
the photons do not exert forces on each
other the dynamics of gluons is much
much more complicated than the dynamics
of photons the last time what I told you
was that one of the and I'm not going to
do the mathematics of this it's not even
fully understood even now but the effect
one of the important effects is that if
you have a source a color a bit of color
with field lines coming out of it again
those field lines are not allowed to end
all right they're not allowed to end but
the effect let's suppose is a that's
quark is an anti quark over here field
lines have to come into it so the field
lines have to be continuous and so forth
I don't want we may not draw more than
that now the effect is that the field
lines interact with each other in a way
that they don't in electrodynamics and
the effect is very simple the field
lines get pulled into bundles which are
called flux tubes the result of which is
that no matter how far apart you pull
two quarks they'll never escape from
each other
because the energy stored in this gooey
piece of glue just increases linearly
with the distance between them all right
that's that's a summary of quantum
chromodynamics but it's also a summary
of gauge theory it's also a summary very
very quick summary of gauge theory
Maxwell like fields sources Gauss's law
making sure you have conservation and
symmetries symmetries having to do with
the conservation laws but more than that
the symmetries telling you how the
particles interact with each other in
terms of emission and absorption there
is one other thing and a gauge theory
and it's the coupling constant the
coupling constant is the analog of the
charge of the electron the charge of the
electron let's talk about what the
charge of the electron means it is of
course
coefficient in a finding diagram when
you emit a photon from a charged
particle the amplitude for that the
quantum mechanical amplitude for that is
the electric charge but if you wanted to
think about it operationally you can
imagine an electric charge slamming into
the of the cathode to the anode cathode
the cathode of a cathode ray tube when
it slams into it it gets accelerated and
the question is what is the probability
that an electron which is stopped
suddenly emits a photon okay the answer
is the square of the electric charge the
square roots really the square of the
electric charge there's some PI's in it
and H bars and things but but basically
the square of the electric charge in
suitable units R is the probability for
emitting a photon so that's what in
quantum mechanics and field theory that
is what the meaning of the electric
charge is it's a measure of the Prabhat
the square of the electric charge is the
probability Y because probabilities are
always squares of amplitudes but that's
the that's the fundamental significance
of the electric charge and the electric
charge is a dimensionless number just
the probability that when you stop an
electron you emit a photon so it's a
dimensionless number it's a small
dimensionless number in with appropriate
sets of definitions the square of the
electric charge really what tends to
come in two things is not quite the
square of the electric charge it's the
square of the electric charge divided by
some four pie for pies are always
floating around in there it's called the
fine-structure constant and the
fine-structure constant which is pretty
much the probability of a photon
emission is a number of about 1% it's
close to being 1 over 137 per famous
number 1 over 137 137 as
no particular significance it's just
numerically about what the
fine-structure constant is and let's
just call it 1% that says there's a 1%
probability of emitting a photon so if
you had a picture that when an electron
hits a cathode ray tube it sends out a
spray of photons that's not right what
is right is that if 137 photons hit the
cathode cathode ray tube on the average
one of them will give off a photon in
that sense electromagnetism is a weak
force or a weak process the probability
of emission is weak all right that
that's the quick summary of gauge theory
what I wanted to do is give you a very
very briefly a rundown on some numbers
and orders of magnitude in various parts
of particle and atomic physics and then
go on to the weak interactions now the
reason I'm giving you a rundown about
numbers is to show you how the weak
interactions quantum chromodynamics is
the theory of the strong interactions
whether the strong interactions was the
word before quantum chromodynamics was
invented for the interactions between
sub-nuclear particles between hadrian's
between protons neutrons mesons and all
the things which are made of quarks and
gluons
so it's theory of strong interactions
and there are electromagnetic
interactions and there are also weak
interactions so I want to spend a little
bit of time with numbers to show you
what where the terminology came from why
one is called weak why the one is called
strong why electromagnetism is sort of
in the middle between the two of them
but let's let's just review a couple of
numbers um first of all in terms of
Units energy distance and time do not
have to be
others different units they're all
related with each other first of all
time and distance really should not be
distinguished in any and sensible set of
units that are useful for fundamental
physics are we can set the speed of
light equal to one and if we do if we
fix the speed of light equal to one then
time and distance have the same units
and we can we can use the same units on
the as far as energy goes we could also
choose to set Planck's constant equal to
one that's a useful thing to do in
quantum mechanics or awful lot of
equations get simpler if you if you set
H bar equal to one
well they don't get a lot simpler they
just gets rid of the H bars but but you
can set H bar equal to one now let me
just remind you there's a connection
between energy e equals H frequency
right or H nu or H bar Omega all the
same thing the units of H bar well we've
set H bar equal to one so in units in
which H bar are equal to one energy is
equal to frequency but what's the units
of frequency one over time number of
oscillations per second so that means
that energy and time have inverse units
to each other you don't need to have a
separate unit for time and energy
anytime you have a unit of energy it
defines also a unit of time now of
course the unit of energy is inverse to
the unit of time so big energies
correspond to small time intervals and
okay so let's let's write down some
connections or and since energy and time
are connected to each other and time and
space have the same units when C is
equal to one then time and space have
units which are just inverse units to
the units of energy so for example
here's a unit of energy one electron
volt
we've used electron volts before one
electron volt cannot be thought of as a
unit of distance but the inverse one
inverse electron volt in other words one
over an electron one inverse electron
volt is a unit of distance and just to
have an idea of what it is it's about 10
to the minus seventh meters one electron
volt is about 10 to the minus seventh
meters so an electron volt is a fairly
small distance but on the scale of
fundamental physics it's not a small
distance 10 to the minus seventh meters
is what I think that oh i Adam is 10 to
the minus 10 meters something like that
yeah okay so it's it's fairly big an
atomic diameter yeah an atomic and we
can convert right and then atomic
diameter of one atom this is the atomic
diameter that's about 10 to the minus 10
meters and so you can convert that to
electron volts how many electron volts
is it or whatever it is an inverse of
about a thousand electron volts a Killah
electron volt an inverse Killah electron
volt is an atomic diameter okay
another fact just converting distance if
we know the distance of size of an atom
then we know the time that it takes
light to go across it all right so the
transit time is another quantity transit
time the time that it takes chance at
the time the time for light to cross an
atomic diameter what is that that's
about 10 to the minus 18 seconds I've
used the fact that light goes at about
10 to the 8th meters per second order of
magnitude 10 to the minus 18 seconds
these are just some numbers that I just
wrote down but a different time scale
all right so this is the time scale for
light to go across an atom the different
times and by an atom I don't mean the
nucleus I mean the the whole atom
another time scale is the time scale
that it takes for
the electron to orbit an atom now you
might think why isn't that just about
the transit time transit time is about
10 to the minus 18 centimeters the
reason is because electromagnetic forces
are fairly weak
because they are fairly weak the force
on and the ultimate reason that they're
weak is because this fine-structure
constant is alpha which is east east
squared over 4 pi that's a small number
of about 1 over 137 another way to say
it is the electromagnetic force on an
electron is weak because of that the
acceleration on the electron is not too
big and the orbit is fairly large the
weak of the force on an object the
larger the orbit is going to be sorry
the slower the electron will move is
what I meant to say the slower the
electron will move and because the
electron moves slowly by comparison with
the speed of light how much slower about
1 percent slower about this much slower
the electron moves around with only
about 1% to speed of light and that
means the orbital time orbital time
that's about 10 to the minus let's say
it's bigger that time is bigger 10 to
the minus 16 seconds another quantity
sometimes of interest is the decay time
for an atom how long does it take for an
atom an excited atom let's say a
hydrogen atom with its electron 1
orbital up from the ground state one
orbit up from the ground state how long
does it take to decay now
that is small EE small with 2 powers of
alpha what are the two powers of alpha
first of all the acceleration of the
electron is small remember the charges
emit radiation when they're accelerated
the acceleration is small
because the force is small so first of
all the acceleration is small the
electron moves around with a relatively
small acceleration compared to what it
could have been if alpha were bigger it
moves around with a small acceleration
but on top of that just like the
electron plowing into the cathode ray
tube there's another factor of alpha
when the electron is accelerated in the
probability that emits a photon so as
the electron goes around here first of
all it's moving with a slow acceleration
and second of all even that acceleration
is not very efficient in producing
photons just because the fine-structure
constant is small the net result is that
the time scale order of magnitude decay
time how long it takes for an atom to
decay decay time is about a nanosecond
10 to the minus 9 seconds much longer
than the orbital time or the transit
time so the main thing is is a variety
of different scales in the atom and
they're all related by the
fine-structure constant they're related
by powers of the fine-structure constant
the fine-structure constant being a
small number there are fairly large
ratios between different time scales
transit orbital and decay time all right
now let's come to hey groans hey drones
are like atoms they're atoms made up out
of quarks we could ask very much the
same kind of questions first of all we
could ask what is the hydronic diameter
the hydronic diameter of a typical
hadron it could be a proton Neutron
mizzen they're all more or less the same
as hydrants hydrants hydrants the
hydraulic diameter is a lot smaller than
the electron sorry then the atom it's a
lot smaller than the atom it's not 10 to
the minus 10 meters it's about 5 orders
of magnitude
smaller ten to the minus 15 centimeters
that's also more or less the diameter of
a nucleus nucleus of course being a few
protons and neutrons is going to be
bigger meters sorry meters Hadron
diameter is about 10 to the minus 15
meters five orders of magnitude smaller
than an atom part of the reason is
because part of these two reasons
there's two reasons why it's small one
of them has to do with the fact that the
constituents are heavier and heavier
things will sit closer to the to the
center the other has to do with
something else that we'll come to in a
minute but it's about five orders of
magnitude smaller the transit time the
transit time has just gotten from the
sides straight forwardly transit time
this is not an independent thing it's
just another measure of the size of the
thing just to get the numbers straight
it's 10 to the minus 23rd seconds so
that's a typical time scale for a well
it's for light to cross the Hadron okay
but now we can also talk about the
orbital motion of quarks how long does
it take for a court to swing around its
wavefunction or swing around the
interior of a proton and there the
answer is about 10 to the minus 23rd
seconds what about the decay time of a
typical hadron and a typical excited
state of a hadron a vibrating hadron or
an oscillating hadron how long does it
take for it to decay and the answer is
about now I'm talking about particular
kinds of decays a decay where you hit a
proton it starts oscillating and then
emits a Payan or
those decays have a lifetime of about
ten to the minus twenty third seconds
different than this hierarchy of scales
here what is the conclusion the
conclusion is the analog of the
fine-structure constant is much bigger
close to one for hydrants in other words
the emission probability if a quark
would get stopped in a fictitious
cathode-ray quark equal rate uber from
of cork flying off the probability for
it to emit a gluon would be about 1
that's what these things indicate here
the hierarchy here is entirely due to
the fine-structure constant the lack of
a hierarchy here can only mean that the
corresponding quantity in quantum
chromodynamics must be close to 1 by now
it's been measured in many ways and it
is much closer to 1 it's much larger
than the the corresponding quantity for
electrodynamics one of the little it is
seen that just special relativity say
passed would be
23 sets of cupcakes like yeah I think
that's a fair statement
yeah it's about as fast as it could be
in other words it's about as fast as it
could be nothing slowing it down this is
why the strong interactions are called
strong now the facts about the numbers
here were known before quantum
chromodynamics and it was understood
that there was no hierarchy of scales
and that's why it was called strong
interactions we now trace it to the
properties of the charge or the
fine-structure constant incidentally for
quantum chromodynamics the analogous
quantity is not really one it's about a
fifth but much bigger than the 1 over
137 here all right so that's that was
just some numbers and some facts about
this there's a bunch of she comes
together to talk about the story so
[Music]
let's go out for QCD okay so this is
called alpha and the other one is called
alpha QCD that's about 0.2 3 or
something like that or you can text to
pay for me right after you learn in
context of paper me write alpha
I never heard Alfa QED referred to as
alpha QED but I think if you were
writing a paper with both of them you
might call the top one alpha QED yes
I've never seen it particularly well I
can't I don't think I've ever seen it
oh oh it's just called alpha sometimes
unshielded one is called the bear alpha
the shielded one is called the
renormalized alpha right okay well that
brings us to the weak interactions weak
interactions are called
weak primarily because the decay times
associated with them are very long
they're much longer than the decay times
associated with with either hadrian's
and they're even they even tend to be
longer than the decay times associated
with atoms so there are processes in
nature decay processes in nature in
which particles elementary or otherwise
decay by weak interactions where the
timescale in other words the half-life
for these decays is far longer than any
scale that can be accounted for by these
by numbers like this so as an example
here's some examples well the lifetime
of the Neutron Neutron is a hey guard
laughs decays neutron goes to electron
proton plus anti neutrino and the
lifetime for that is about 12 minutes
that's absurdly long on particle physics
scales part of the reason is easy but it
hardly accounts for the for the
extraordinary stability of the neutron
part of the reason is the neutron is
only a little bit bigger than the
combined masses of the electron the
proton and the neutron neutrino let's
just uh see somebody how about their
pocket calculator the mass of the
neutron is 940 MeV
I don't 940 about 940 the mass of the
proton is about 939 I think the actual
difference between them is about one and
a half MeV but then there's the electron
which has a mass of about half an MeV
altogether out of this 940 almost a
thousand MeV the difference of mass of
the proton the amount of available mass
left over is tiny as 0.1 percent or less
if the neutron was slightly lighter than
the sum of these masses it could not
decay at all just energy conservation
would not allow it remember masses
energy it would not have enough energy
to decay and still leave over some
energy for kinetic energy of these
particles so if the neutron was exactly
the same as the sum of the energy of the
electron the proton a neutrino the sum
of the mass of them
it wouldn't be able to decay at all if
you gave it a mass tiny tiny tiny tiny
bit above that it would be able to decay
but it would take a very long time that
the K would be very slow so part of the
slowness or the long lifetime of the
neutron is attributable to the fact that
there's very little energy available for
the decay to take place but given that
that's hardly the bulk of the story 12
minutes is so absurdly long long that
there's something much much more than
that going on another example let's see
what do I have it I guess I didn't write
it down another example of this is
called a weak decay for obvious reasons
it's called a weak decay another example
is a charged PI on let's say a PI minus
a charged PI on decays to an electron
electron has negative charge and an anti
neutrino are yes and an anti-neutrino
that's another possible decay charge pi
on goes to an electron and antineutrino
a positively charged PI on could become
a positron and a neutrino the life time
for that I believe is about 10
nanoseconds longer than these atomic
decay times and atomic decay times are
very very long by comparison with
particle physics decay times now this
there is a decay of the charge pawns
through these particles is another decay
involving nuan's we're going to come to
muon soon enough similar to electrons
but the point is not the particles that
they decay into but two things first of
all they also decay very
slowly nanoseconds but there's plenty of
energy available for these theta decays
these the case I'm not suppressed by the
fact that the energies of the initial
and all the masses of the initial and
final states are very close to each
other so there's something else going on
are in weak interactions whatever we can
whatever weak interactions are there's
something that makes them proceed very
very slowly and weakly all right so
that's what we come to next is weak
interactions are the primary or oldest
example of which is the decay of the
neutron the beta decay of the neutron
called beta because electrons are
originally called beta waves
all right that's and this is called the
beta decay of the PI arm and in fact
it's quite similar quite similar physics
goes into both of them so to understand
what's going on we need to understand
about some more particles particles that
we haven't come to yet the leptons
let's go back to the quarks for a moment
and let me just make a table of the
different kinds of quarks horizontally
or make a sequence here which will be
red blue and green these are the colors
of quarks then along here let me list
the up quark the down quark the charm
quark the strange quark the top quark
and the bottom quark they're each one of
these boxes is filled there are red blue
and green up quarks let's put an X there
there's an X here there's an X here
there's an X here X here X here and so
forth these X's represent all the
possible quarks that exist now quantum
chromodynamics has to do with symmetries
which connect red to green to blue has
to do with these unitary transformations
which mix up the colors of quarks they
do not those symmetries do not mix
horizontally and su 2 su 3 symmetry a
color symmetry may rotate an up red
quark into an up blue quark or an up
green quark and the nature of the
symmetry is to act vertically to mix up
things this way this way it also at the
same time will mix the different down
quarks the different colors of down
quarks the same symmetry will mix the
different colors of charm quarks and
strange quarks and so forth so the color
symmetry acts vertically it mixes up the
different rows here
yes the unitary matrices mix up red
green and blue I might have done better
to put the rows where the columns are in
the columns with a rose R but no it's
okay it's good it's good no no it's good
that's good right the weak interactions
are associated with symmetries which act
horizontally in this picture they mix up
with down they mix at the same time that
they mix up with down they mix charm
with strange and they mix top with
bottom let me just remind you that an up
quark has the same properties apart for
its mass same properties as a charm
quark or a top quark the down quarks are
similar to strange quarks and bottom
quarks ups have charged 2/3 downs have
charged minus 2/3 same here and here on
so these are symmetries which mix if you
like upness with down this at the same
time charm this with strangeness and top
this with bottomless mixes these up the
symmetries those symmetries
what would you care to speculate on what
group might be involved a su 2 because
it acts on things on doublets we simply
have three doublets here and never they
don't take up the charm or up to top
they simply act on up and down
horizontally among pairs of things a
group su 2 and it is a gauge symmetry in
other words it is also comes together
with forces with gauge bosons with
interactions and with gauge interaction
or gauge fields we're going to get to
those short enough but we've left out
something from this table here it's kind
of as if there was a fourth color now
the reason the fourth row here is not
usually identified as a color
and the reason is because the particles
do not interact with the gluons but
nevertheless it is another row here
another row in which there are particles
which are filled in here and in a
certain sense there or not in a certain
sense they are also doublets these
particles are also doublets and also get
mixed up under this su 2 symmetry which
moves things horizontally what are they
what are those particles they're the
leptons so in a sense the fourth color
could be thought of as lepton number but
what are the leptons the leptons are
first of all in the first column here
there are analogous to the upload
analogous to the down there is the
electron the electron is a lepton but
its partner its partner is the neutrino
but there are different neutrinos
there's not only one neutrino this is
called the electron neutrino what comes
in the next column muon the muon in
every respect except for mass is the
same as an electron just as in every
respect except for mass the charm quark
is like an up quark or the strange quark
is like a down quark and together with
it there's its own neutrino the muon
neutrino and finally the last one is
called the tau and nu sub tau all of the
charged leptons incidentally neutrinos
of course as you might guess from their
name are electrically neutral the
electrons muons and Tau's have charged -
warn okay they put they are put under
the down column here not because their
charge is the same
the down charge but because the
difference between the charges of the
two is the same as the charge difference
up here what's the difference between
the charge of an up and a down
two-thirds minus minus one-third so the
difference between this column and this
column is plus one unit of charge the
difference between this column in this
column is also one unit of charge one
sorry zero minus negative one so as you
go from here to here you decrease charge
by one unit as you go horizontally now
should we take a break for five minutes
let's take a break for five minutes and
then I will tell you about the W bosons
W bosons are the gauge bosons of the
weak interactions all right so let's say
let's try now to see if we can make a
microscopic gauge theory of the weak
interactions ah ah as I said the weak
interactions are based on a gauge theory
which mixes up to down the tree no two
electron and so forth and so rather than
to get into mathematics for the moment
the mathematics of the group su 2 which
will come back to let's think a little
more simply we've seen that in various
situations the gauge bosons typically
have the quantum numbers or the quantum
properties of a particle and an anti
particle in the case of the
[Music]
in the case of the quantum
chromodynamics it is a quark and an
antiquark so that's why we had nine
gauge bosons and so forth or eight
removing the trace so we could we could
start by saying let's look at the
possibilities of gauge bosons which have
the properties of of a particle and the
antiparticle but it let's not
distinguish between whether we're
talking about quarks red quarks blue
quarks green quarks or leptons let's
just say a particle from this column
with an anti particle of this column and
for simplicity let's just focus on the
leptons you'll see in a moment that you
get the same thing if you focused on the
quarks but let's focus on the leptons
and talk about objects that we could
make with a lepton and an anti lepton
alright first of all we could have some
simple things electron with a positron
now I don't really literally mean
electrons and positrons okay
we could have electrons and positrons
electrons and positrons have no charge
at all so let's drop that for a minute
we'll come back to it there are things
which have properties of electrons and
anti electrons neutrinos and
antineutrinos
but more interesting for the moment is
the combination of electron antineutrino
so what is the charge of an object which
has the the consumed conserved
quantities the same properties as an
electron with stuck on top of an anti
neutrino well let's just focus on its
charge its electric charge its electric
charge is minus 1 neutrino is neutral
electron electron has negative charge so
whatever this object is
it has negative electric charge let's
give it a name and let's call it a gauge
boson let's assume that it is also a
gauge boson gauge boson means that it
behaves like the Maxwell field the whole
same thing but it has negative charge
what's called W W that's the traditional
name for it W - why - because it has
negative electric charge we could that
was there was this one with this one we
could have taken down quark with it I
guess
anti up quark yeah down quark what
happens if you take down quark with anti
up quark I'm as charged do you get again
- same as this down quark with anti up
quark would also have - charge so if you
like you could also imagine that the W -
has the same properties as a down quark
and an anti up quark in other words it's
one from the second column and anti one
from the first column that's the
property that it has let's call it W for
week in fact I think W is originally the
notation for week the negatively charged
W boson and of course there's also a
positively charged boson W boson which
is like anti down with an up or like
positron u plus with a neutrino a plus
with a neutrino would be a W plus let's
suppose the pattern is pretty similar to
quantum chromodynamics that the W bosons
are like either photons on the one hand
or like gluons which means that they
would be objects which could be emitted
from
the leptons there would be objects which
will allow a lepton of one kind
let me not label it a lepton of one kind
to become a lepton of another kind by
emitting a W boson let's see if we can
find some examples are an electron can
emit a W - to become ametrine o electron
becomes neutrino by emission of a w -
you see the action of the gauge bosons
is to do the same kind of transition
that the symmetry is ultimately going to
be imagined to do to mix electron into
neutrino in very much the same way that
the colors got mixed by emitting gluons
you could follow the lines if you like
and say the electron and the anti
neutrino over here can be imagined to be
a w- boson same pattern let's just draw
it by saying a w- is emitted but that's
not all you can do with the w- you can
also have a Down quark go to an up quark
with a w- that also works and in fact
the w- is an object which can be emitted
in a transition from let's see from the
right column to the left column a red
down quark can become a red up quark by
emitting a w blue down quark can become
a blue up quark by emitting a w likewise
for green but you can go further the
strange quark not the strange quark the
yeah the strange quark can become a
charmed quark that's another one strange
quark charmed quark again w- so this new
symmetry this is an idea of a new
symmetry or jacked horizontally and only
horizontally between neighboring pairs
here introduces the possibility of gauge
bosons which cause transitions between
electron neutrino down quark and up
quark strange quark and charm quark now
a w+ + w- our anti particles of each
other
the meaning of that is that you can flip
these diagrams put the W - down W here
but when you flip it it becomes a w+ so
a w+ can be absorbed by an electron plus
a unit of charge - the unit of charge to
become a neutrino so a whole family of
different processes are codified by this
one vertex here we can turn them upside
down neutrino goes to you know you know
we're allowed to do we've done this
things before and that's the basic new
element of the weak interactions
actually that's all young
it's not clear to me why you have a w-
in all three of these cases there's
electric charge conservation couldn't be
w+ when you accept i don't know what is
w means w is the name of a particle it's
the name of another gauge be out of the
charge the charge conservation doesn't
it's could be - right
but well I haven't seen any reason why
it should be the same part of it or well
okay that that that's right but what it
comes down to in the end is an empirical
fact it's the empirical fact that the
symmetry of the weak interactions acts
simultaneously on all of these doublets
here when an up goes to a down a charm
has to go to a strange a towel has to go
to a top has to go to a bottom and the
leptons have to mix with each other
simultaneously the implication of that
the implication of that from a practical
point of view is simply it's the same
symmetry which acts it's the same gauge
bosons which are which are there you
could have imagined a theory in which
it's quite mathematically consistent to
imagine a theory where different W type
bosons would have a bit been emitted by
up quarks charm quarks or tau quarks or
even leptons right it's a fact of nature
a fact of nature that nature is simpler
than might have been ah that the same
gauge bosons cause transitions between
any row any point row you know what I
mean I'm going to get tongue-tied if I
try to say it okay well first of all how
do we what what processes can we explain
present yeah can he can
[Music]
and negative associated oh yes yes yes
yes you can flip arrows and you can flip
lines yes yes certainly you can flip the
arrows yeah absolutely absolutely and
you can also flip lines up and down in
various ways for example another way you
could flip the line is you could take
this up quark here have it instead of
going out instead of an up quark going
out an anti up quark comes in whenever
you flip a line from past to future or
from future to past you'll also change
from particle to anti particle
brightness library another Knights there
is strange in part wrong
yes so that's the same as a down in time
oh yeah grateful 30 yeah that's a
strange in part wrong it's not literally
a strange and an anti charm it's just a
rule that tells you that whatever these
W bosons are they're associated with
transitions from one column to the other
did I sorry strange all right electron
to neutrino strange to charm is that
wrong
who said it was an anti charm all right
if you follow the lines like that at the
point where the line turns around it has
to be thought of as an anti particle
right okay or if you like you can always
think of it as strange anti charm coming
in and making a W boson okay just keep
in mind whenever you flip from the past
to the future if you want to know what a
W boson will decay to let's read it that
downward it will decay to a strange and
an anti charm and that really can happen
yeah so we create a W boson from like
electron and a neutrino anti and
neutrino and then call the W boson to
change into like a train get a charm
exactly that's where some of these
processes are going to come from now so
let's let's think about the various
processes let's start just for fun let's
start with the decay of the pie - what
is it by - a pie - is a quark and an
antiquark with altogether negative
charge so let's say a quark and an
antiquark with negative charge had
better be that here's the pie - that's
equal to
a down quark and an antiquark down and
anti up now what kind of down an anti up
do let's see if we can find down an anti
up here here it is right here down and
anti up can become a w- that's a
possible transition ah that is allowed
by the physics of w bosons so here's a
w- but now a w- can do something else
a w- here is let's say here is a w+
let's put w+ upstairs here sorry this is
w- now and let's put the neutrino
downstairs anti neutrino and read this
as saying that w- goes to what electron
antineutrino so w- can go to electron
antineutrino and here it is e - ordinary
electron so that's the basic underlying
process that governs the beta decay of
the negatively charged pi on into a into
a electron and an anti-neutrino now
which anti neutrino is it there are
three distinct anti neutrinos it's the
electron antineutrino over here so it's
the electron antineutrino
but it can also I didn't draw all the
various possibilities but any place you
saw an electron you can put a muon
anyplace and as long as you carry along
the muon neutrino so another process is
muon
and I'm you on the tree no and just for
clarity this is not strictly a Fineman
diagram right this is just showing an
interaction it's pretty close to a fine
well except for the time direction oh
yeah okay antenna I don't know why all
of a sudden I change directions yeah for
some reason yeah right time is the time
is now going horizontally I've become a
computer scientist and they they
measured their yeah yeah they do
right yeah it's pretty much yeah let's
good we turn it up I can't do that
easily but yeah yeah that is essentially
a Fineman diagram describing the decay
of the pie - too demure as it happens
the for technical reasons having to do
with some complications and Fineman
diagrams that are not interesting to us
as it happens the primary decay or
primary I mean the most probable the
most probable decay of the pie - is to
the muon antineutrino not to the
electron antineutrino it's a technical
point of no no special interest to us it
just happens to be that way
will it be consistent instead of peace
considering these moment diagrams with
with the time deal is more like a
chemical equilibrium deal which way
you're going well both things can happen
both things gamma is not there so but
not in chemical equilibrium we're in
empty space when empty space except
somebody made a pie - a pie - was
created how a pie - might be created by
some nucleons coming together and
creating by strong interactions by
strong interactions of pie - might be
created now that pie - is just going
along and saying wait a minute I can
decay if I like into a neutrino and a
muon then of course the neutrino and the
muon have enough energy kinetic energy
to fly off and they won't come back
together again because they've departed
they've gone away okay on the other hand
it is true that if you were to take a
muon and an anti-neutrino and fire them
toward each other there would be a
probability that they would make up I -
so yes you can read it both ways let's
go like in one dimension you have a su 3
the other su 2 is it possible if you
like combine them into an issue six or
something this your 5 su 5 that's your
five not two times three two plus three
you know all right
su five but not tonight tonight we want
to get to su two that we'll all be happy
if we get the basic ideas of su 2 all
right now keep in mind we're doing
something a little bit funny because we
have su two has how many generators
three so how many gauge bosons should it
have three so fall we only have W + + W
- there must be another one looking
around and that other one must be
associated somehow was something like
electron anti electron and neutrino anti
neutrino but we'll come through it just
like the Yahoo will come through it
there is a third gauge boson lurking
around and it does play a big role in
the weak interactions but it didn't play
a big role historically in the weak
interactions just because for reasons
we'll come to historically it was the W
boson which was the first to be
conjectured nothing but speaking of
historically was the weak or the strong
force sort of suspected first
oh of course all right so let's talk
about the history the history of these
forces goes back to Becker L goes back
to radioactivity alpha beta and gamma
decay alpha decay was what a mission of
a two protons and two neutrons from a
nucleus that's a strong interaction it's
part of the theory of hadrons in nuclei
beta decay that was this one right here
weak interactions and gamma decay photon
so historically they happened at the
same time in the same experiment
the energy conservation how it works are
you assuming some kinetic okay um yeah
the energy card let's recover you never
worry about the energy conservation in
intermediate states like this if the
energy of the intermediate state doesn't
match the energies of the initial and
final state it just means that the
intermediate state can only last for a
very short time there's an energy time
uncertainty principle you can violate
the energies in a Fineman diagram for
short periods of time so don't worry
about conservation of energy between
here and here the only energy we have to
worry about is the initial energy in the
final energy okay so let's worry about
it
a Payan has an energy of about a mass
let's suppose the Payan is at rest the
mass of the Payan is roughly about a
hundred and forty MeV all right what is
the energy of the of the muon and the
neutrino well first of all it's the rest
energy of the muon and then the Trino
okay and the rest energy the rest mass
of them the mass of the neutrino sorry
the mass of the muon I think is about a
hundred MeV I forget exactly and the
mass of a neutrino is for practical
purposes zero too small to be important
yeah so there's more energy to start
with than the energy in the in the
masses of the two final particles does
that mean it can't happen no it just
means that the particles will go off and
carry some kinetic energy so the
difference between the energy on this
side and the sums of the masses on this
side is just the kinetic energy of the
outgoing particles that's the energy
balance the momentum also has to be
conserved and that means if the Payan
was at rest to begin with the momentum
of the muon and the momentum of the
neutrino have to be equal and opposite
and they'll go out back-to-back so to
speak if you analyze the neutron you can
say I'm going to do that now yeah let's
do the neutron decay right now see how
Neutron works oh let's do something
simpler first let's do the muon decay
the muon is also something that can
decay so let's take the muon here's the
muon moving along now what can the muon
do the muon can become a neutrino sub
muon and emit a W what kind of w w -
right become a W - and a neutrino okay
but now one of the things that W - can
do is it can become an electron and an
anti-neutrino so this w - can now become
an electron and an anti-neutrino of the
electron variety can this happen the
only thing that would press it can
happen not only can happen this is the
way the muon decays are the muon decays
because it is sufficiently much heavier
than the electron much heavier than the
electron about 200 times heavier than
the electron the neutrinos are
practically massless so the energy
balance is you have about 100 MeV here a
half an MeV here and the rest goes off
in kinetic energy so that's an example
of a what's called a purely lepton ik
process no quarks in it at all
yeah so it's one neutrino one anti
neutrino and an electron okay so that
happens and that's the primary the
primary decay it's the only decay of the
muon so the muon is an unstable particle
because of this but the reason the muon
is unstable and not the electron is just
the muon happens to be heavy enough to
be able to decay to the electron the
electron is not heavy enough to decay to
the muon so in a sense it's an accident
of the masses the same is true of the
Tau incidentally the Tau can also decay
to two other leptons but all right
that's the mew decay and notice the
components are the same the basic
components are the same a transition
from one column to another followed by a
w and then the W makes another
transition from one column to the other
or if you like a decay from one column
to the other all right what about the
the decay of the neutron decay of the
neutron would it be consistent to say
the purpose of the linear accelerators
per se is to effectively increase the
mass of the electron so that it can now
go the other direction absolutely yeah
you know changing ass you just put man
but nothing absolutely yeah but that's
exactly right
okay we were going to do Neutron decay
so the neutron is maybe I better switch
to vertical don't want a vertical
vertical notation back to vertical
Neutron is three quarks two down quarks
and an up quark write my minus 4/3 plus
2/3 sorry minus 2/3 yes that's a neutron
electrically neutral neutral neutrons
coming in ok now what is possible first
of all we can have the up quark become a
down quark and emit some sort of W but
that will give us three down quarks
three down quarks is a fine thing
there's nothing wrong with three down
quarks except that the mass of three
down quarks of the L of a particle with
three down quarks is always too heavy
for the neutron to decay so that's not
what happens what about one of the down
quarks the down quark can emit a W
become an up quark this is again a W
minus the down quark emits of W minus
becomes an up quark and now we have two
up quarks and a down quark up up down
where's that called that's a proton at
the W core the W does what the W always
does it can decay it decays to an
electron and an anti-neutrino electron
antineutrino so that's the that's the
beta decay of the neutron could it decay
into a muon and a neutrino not enough
energy the muon is too heavy so that
there wouldn't be enough energy left
over
or for the muon but other than that if
it were not for that it could happen
another way to say it is if you could
jam some more energy into the neutron
how can you do it you hit it you give it
a shove you give the neutron a whack you
excite it and if you're excited enough
it can decay to a proton a neutrino anti
neutrino and a muon but without somehow
providing that extra energy the neutron
will only decay to the proton electron
and antineutrino okay now let's come
let's see where are we I think we're
finished for tonight I think we'll
finish for that but remember we have a
puzzle and the puzzle is why is it that
the weak interactions give such slow
decay rates and I can think of one
reason namely the coupling constant or
the analog of the of the fine-structure
constant could be ridiculously small so
that the probability of emitting these W
bosons would be very very small that is
not the reason the fine-structure
constant for the weak interactions is
about the same for electromagnetism that
is not the reason the reason is
something else and we'll come to
something else next time
Lagrangian the Lagrangian is invariant
under those operations that's exactly
what it means I didn't want to start
writing bunches of lagrangian's so I've
used the shorthand of saying as a
symmetry right but that's what it means
yeah for more please visit us at
stanford.edu